<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the magistrates and ministers of the city of Gloucester, from the calumnies of Mr. Robert Bacon, in his printed relation of his usage there, which he intitles, The spirit of prelacy yet working, or truth from under a cloud. Together with ten questions discussed, which tend to the discovery of close antinomianisme. / By John Corbet minister, and chaplain to Major generall Massie. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Corbet, John, 1620-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6267B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E337_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200828</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861462</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113599</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113599)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E337[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the magistrates and ministers of the city of Gloucester, from the calumnies of Mr. Robert Bacon, in his printed relation of his usage there, which he intitles, The spirit of prelacy yet working, or truth from under a cloud. Together with ten questions discussed, which tend to the discovery of close antinomianisme. / By John Corbet minister, and chaplain to Major generall Massie. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Corbet, John, 1620-1680.</author>
                  <author>Nicanor, Lysimachus, 1603-1641,</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Bostock dwelling at the signe of the Kings Head in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wrongly ascribed in the Wing catalogue (2nd ed., 1972) to John Corbet, 1603-1641 [i.e. Lysimachus Nicanor].</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Bacon, Robert. The spirit of prelacie, yet working (Wing B370).</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bacon, Robert, --  M.A. --  Spirit of prelacie, yet working.</term>
               <term>Antinomianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113599:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE MAGISTRATES And Miniſters of the City of <hi>GLOVCESTER,</hi> From the Calumnies of Mr. <hi>Robert Bacon,</hi> in his Printed Relation of his uſage there; which he intitles, <hi>The Spirit of Prelacy yet working, Or Truth from under a Cloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with ten Queſtions diſcuſſed, which tend to the diſcovery of Cloſe Antinomianiſme.</p>
            <p>By JOHN CORBET Miniſter, and Chaplain to Major Generall MASSIE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 18. 17.</bibl>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe ſeemeth juſt: but his neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Bostock</hi> dwelling at the Signe of the Kings Head in Pauls Church-yard. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113599:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113599:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> LORD VISCOUNT SAY and SEAL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Find my ſelf, with many others, repreſented to Your Honors view in as odious Colours as Malice it ſelf could deblazon, in Mr. <hi>Bacons</hi> Printed Relation of his uſage in <hi>Glouceſter.</hi> Whereupon I conceive my ſelf bound to maintain my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity both in reſpect of my perſon as a Chriſtian, and of my calling as a Miniſter. I have therefore publiſhed this Vindication, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſent to Your Lordſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching You to receive it as an humble yet neceſſary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe to Your Lordſhips Juſtice. Had I declined this Appeal, I might either be thought guilty, or to derogate from Your equity and impartiality. But I know that Your great and Noble Spirit highly diſdains the patronage of the leaſt falſhood, and will condeſcend to a Vindication of the Truth from what ever hand it comes. Let your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour be pleaſed to conceive of me, as one who deſires and ſhould joy in your favourable opinion. My prayer is, that according to Your renowned Piety your Name may be precious and Honourable, for promoving a bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and the fixed Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt: and for this the Souls of the people of God ſhall bleſſe You.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors humbly devoted Servant in the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>JOHN CORBET.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113599:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Aldermen</hi> of the City of GLOUCESTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Am conſtrained to publiſh an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Bacons</hi> Relation, wherein both you, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of your City with divers others, are vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traduced. It troubles me that <hi>Glouceſter</hi> ſhould come in queſtion or be ſpoken of in ſuch a ſlender buſineſſe; yet ſince it is made publick I cannot neglect it. Beſides, greater Events do take their firſt Riſe from ſmall beginnings: And I know not what influence that vain Relation may have on the publick, if it paſſe uncontrolled. Unto you therefore I tender this Vindication, and caſt my ſelf upon your Cenſure where theſe things were acted. I value my Reputation with you, and I truſt ſhall ſtill behold my native place with comfort, and the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of a good Conſcience, which I can never hope to do if mine integrity fail me. The Lord make you valiant for his Truth, and according to your power to avenge the Quarrel of His Covenant, and to contend for the Faith which was once gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Saints.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>John Corbet.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113599:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He preſent times do ſeem to groan under the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Books, which are thruſt out into the world by a Generall opinion of ſelf-ſufficiencie. Inſomuch that the unskilfull Reader is quite op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and inſtead of making progreſſe in the way of ſolid truth, ſits down amaz'd: Wherfore I ſhould eaſily reſolve never to divert the very looſer thoughts of men, by any object caſt before them, which according to <hi>Solomons</hi> expreſſion, doth neither help to abate the number of that which is wanting, nor to make ſtrait that which is crooked; <hi>i. e.</hi> neither to make up the defects of the ſtate of knowledge, nor to cure it's diſtempers. And for this cauſe I much bewail my unhappineſſe, that I am forced to the publick view in a buſineſſe in it ſelf mean and ſlender, but now to be undertaken of pure neceſſity. Which I ſpeak not to detract from the value of the leaſt materiall cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance appertaining to Religion: but all inferior paſſages are not worthy to trouble the world with a large declaration of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. Beſides points of high concernment were then ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly handled in a ſubitaneous diſpute. The reading of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply I chalenge as a due from them that are acquainted with, have heard of, or are any way intereſſed in this Conteſtation, that the truth may be cleared. But for them that are ſtrangers, or have their judgements equally poyſed, if they will be ſo cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as to behold, they may judge where the ſpirit of bitternes, and calumny doth lie under the inſinuations of a ſweet ſpirit of meekneſſe. Let none expect things of an higher nature then the matter it ſelf will reach. And for my Reply, 'tis the labour of ſix dayes without the advantage of my Papers, and the help of others ingaged with me, when the Relation hath been written well nigh two yeers ſince. Let this be accepted from one whoſe hearts deſire is for the glory of Sion in the Churches Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to the genuine, not the conſtrained and rack't ſenſe of the Nationall Covenant.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113599:4"/>
            <head>The ſumme and ſubſtance of that whole buſineſſe, which is ſtyled by Mr. <hi>Bacon, That great and publick conteſtation had in Glouceſter, July</hi> 1644.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Bacon</hi> arriving at <hi>Glouceſter</hi> as a meer ſtranger (whether upon a call to ſupply the room of an abſent Miniſter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf knows it matters not) was permitted, &amp; by my ſelf once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted to preach there. His firſt Sermon in publick was upon the Monethly Faſt before the greateſt, if not the onely Congregation in the City that day. Divers Miniſters then preſent were much troubled not onely at particular Doctrines delivered, but at the whole frame of his Prayer and Sermon, as being no way ſutable to a ſolemn Humiliation. The Magiſtrates and religious perſons of a better underſtanding and temper, took the like offence <hi>Sine Ira, &amp; odio,</hi> for they knew him not, nor his former converſation. After this, he preached other Sermons, to ſupply the abſence of Mr <hi>Hart;</hi> the drift of which Sermons ſhall be declared in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of particulars. The ſerious people had thoughts of heart concerning this thing, others diſcourſed, and the whole City was quickly filled with this buſineſſe. The Magiſtrates were as much troubled as the Miniſters, and that chiefly upon their own judgement, not others information. The Mayor ſtopp'd the courſe of his preaching (as himſelf relates) which reſtraint was taken off by the Governor for a further triall. The generall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was heightned. Whereupon it was moved among the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, that he ſhould depart the City: but this motion was again let fall, and 'twas ordered that he ſhould come to a diſpute or Conference in the Governors Chamber the next Lords day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Evening Exerciſe. The Mayor, Governor, Committee, and many principall Citizens together with the Miniſters met at the time and place appointed. The reſult of our Conference was to be penned, that there might be no ſhifting on either party. And becauſe Mr. <hi>Bacons</hi> preaching was full of affected ambiguity, we deſired in the firſt place to propoſe certain Queſtions concerning fundamentall Doctrine, and thoſe onely upon which his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing did immediately reflect. And though he pleaded this deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be the way of the High Commiſſion Court, yet the Equity thereof ſhall be made good. For the debate of theſe Queſtions, Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> was allowed about three dayes preparation: But he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113599:4"/>
of accepting the Diſpute, brought in at large his own ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Queſtions, and his Judgement upon them. And when the Errors and impertinencies thereof were clearly argued, he utterly diſclaimed all diſpute, referring us to his Paper, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring our Anſwer in writing, in which way there could be no end of the Controverſie. Yet he received from my ſelf an Anſwer in writing. Nevertheleſſe his own partie made great outcryes of palpable injurie in the manage of the Conference. Whereupon for a generall ſatisfaction a publick Diſputation was had in the Colledge between Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> and my ſelf. Which being ended, the ſame day the Committee deſiring the Miniſters to be preſent, drew up an Order injoyning him to quit the Town. This Order was diſobeyed: whereupon a ſecond was drawn up more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then the former, but that alſo ſlighted, in purſuance wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Governor commanded a ſmall party of horſe to be his Convoy through places of danger to other quarters of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and from theſe he received civill uſage according to his own teſtimony. This is the truth of his remarkable Story, which he brought forth in ſo large a Declaration, profeſſing that this Argument might have ſwollen into a greater Volume, but that there is no end of Diſputes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>An Examination of the particulars in Mr. <hi>Bacons</hi> Relation of his uſage in <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Wherin if many triviall circumſtances ſhall nauſeat the ſerious Reader, let him take notice that I am bound to follow an extravagant Adverſary ſtep by ſtep: And for my faithfulneſſe herein, firſt let him look back upon my Appeals. Secondly, that theſe things were acted before many witneſſes, to whom I am well known, and with whom I value my Repute. Tbirdly, I am aſſured of the concurrence of godly Miniſters; but am now conſtrained to appear alone, becauſe haſte is my greateſt advantage.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>I Cannot paſſe by the frontiſpice without obſervation, which would raiſe the thoughts of the Reader to expect ſome great and admirable diſcovery. And what is it? <hi>The ſpirit of Prelacy yet working, or truth from under a cloud.</hi> What an incongruous beginning yet proportionable to the reſt! If the latter part of the Title be an explanation of the former, as ſuch connexions would import; <hi>then the ſpirit of Prelacy yet working is Truth from under a Cloud.</hi> What then is intituled unto this great myſtery. <hi>A Relation of that great
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113599:5"/>
and publick Conteſtation had in Gloucester. July</hi> 1644. Certainly this Relater will abate nothing of his value. Such Titles are fit for ſome generall meeting of eminent perſons, a diſpute before the repreſentative Body of a Kingdom, or ſome famous reſult and notable periods of the debates of a Nationall Aſſembly. Beſides 'tis called that great Conteſtation, as if the whole Kingdom ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did or were bound to take notice of it.</p>
            <p>In the intimation to the Reader what greater advantage could I wiſh, <hi>Quam quod accuſatori maxime optandum conſitentem reum.</hi> He doth freely confeſſe, that nothing was done in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>but in the eye of Authority, and by their order.</hi> Let it be conſidered that this Authority was the joynt conſent of the Civill and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Government of Glouceſter, a place famous for it's fidelitie to the Kingdoms Cauſe in the greateſt ſtrait, that the Parliament was as yet ever caſt into ſince the beginning of the War, a place which was a refuge and Sanctuary to godly Miniſters and people in their diſtreſſe, which they that were refreſhed will at this day acknowledge.</p>
            <p>He deſires to give <hi>an Experiment of the ſeaſonableneſſe of Mr.</hi> Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans <hi>caution to the Parliament, that the Clergie</hi> (ut vocant) <hi>may not carry on their own ſelf deſignes,</hi> that is in plain Engliſh, to hinder the ſetling of Church-Government. It is well known that they who retard or hinder the Reformation, muſt needs drive on ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes.</p>
            <p>He ſpeaks alſo of my Reply, and a Rejoynder made by himſelf at that time. In this point I accuſe him of palpable injury in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing his own ſtating of the Queſtions, and concealing my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, which was not onely given in to him in private, but was read at the publick Diſputation. Thus hath he prevaricated in a main part of his Relation. Then ſuch partialitie what can be more unworthy of an ingenuous Adverſary? As for his Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I never ſaw it, nor remember that I heard of it. What is this more then to think a Rejoynder, yea a meer nothing? For, <hi>de non entibus &amp; non apparentibus eadem eſt ratio.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Relation it ſelf.</head>
               <p>IT is ſaid, that an offence was taken, but non given at a Sermon preached by him on the publick Faſt day. <hi>Anſ.</hi> An offence may
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113599:5"/>
be given, and juſtly taken not onely at things unlawfull, but at things unexpedient. As for this particular caſe, the whole frame of the Prayer and Sermon was no way fit for a publick Faſt, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſin almoſt wholly omitted, the work of Humiliation diſparaged, the Doctrine of Repentance, and Contrition or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe of heart, as it is taught by our Miniſters of the good old way of the Non Conformiſts, was condemned for Popery, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though through many circumlocutions, mazes, and ambiguous tearms. An inſtance was given in an Allegory taken out of the <hi>Crums of Comfort,</hi> called <hi>A Remedy for a ſin-ſick Soul,</hi> and is inſerted in the cloſe of his Relation, which he hath tearmed <hi>a ridiculous and ſoul-killing Medicine.</hi> This Medicine was compoſed by an eminent Divine, and though it may be queſtioned whether it be ſightly ſo to allegorize, yet it follows not that 'tis either ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous or ſoul-killing: and being deveſted of its party coloured coat to appear in proper and plain tearms, it will be found to carry no diſproportion to the Analogy of Faith; Though he cals it <hi>rather the language of Rome then Canaan.</hi> But this was not that ſpark which was blown up into ſo great flame, but was onely an inſtance ſelected by him on purpoſe, becauſe moſt eaſie as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be made odious. Neither was the Faſt-Exerciſe the ſole ground of the Controverſie, but each Sermon increaſed the fire.</p>
               <p>The firſt Charge is given in againſt Mr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Holford, and my ſelf for ſolliciting the Mayor to ſuſpend his preaching.</hi> As for Mr <hi>Marſhall</hi> whether he did ſo I know not, neither doth it much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the buſineſſe, but I muſt tell the world, that Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> hath traduced this able, painfull, and godly Miniſter with a groſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, <hi>that he lived and preached among the Cavaleers.</hi> For he hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved within three miles of Glouceſter for many yeers before the War, and never removed from his own Charge, and whereas he had ſometimes a weekly Lecture at <hi>Berkly,</hi> he diſcontinued it when that place was poſſeſſed by the Kings Forces. For my ſelf I remember not that I made known any grievance to the Mayor concerning him, before he was publickly queſtioned: but I know aſſuredly that I never ſolicited that he might be ſuſpended, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I move one ſyllable againſt his ſecond liberty of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained from the Governor, as I might eaſily have done.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113599:6"/>
Beſides, the Mayor ſent for me to the Town Chamber at ſeverall times complaining of this Man. And once meeting Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> in the Tolſey I appealed to the Mayor, and others preſent, whether I had been his accuſer. Mr. <hi>Holford</hi> is accuſed of labouring to keep in with both ſides. This is one mans report; but thus much I can ſay for my Brother in the Miniſtery, that he was an open, and earneſt oppoſer of Sectaries, and 'tis hard for me to conceive (let others judge) that a knowing man ſhould ſeek reputation or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by under-hand dealing, or comply with that party, whoſe ſpirits were imbittered againſt him.</p>
               <p>His reſtraint being taken off, and he applying himſelf to clear the Doctrine of Repentance (though indeed he muzzled the truth thereof) he tels us, that <hi>one Wheeler ſet himſelf to take Notes of his Prayer and Sermon to ſtir up adverſaries by giving information, which we are ſaid to receive with all readineſſe.</hi> What a remarkable and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy paſſage, as if we had need of Spies to pry into that which was delivered before ſo many witneſſes: or that one mans informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were the ground of all the following trouble, which was raiſed by a generall complaint. But Mr. <hi>Wheeler</hi> profeſſeth that he was once reſolved not to hear him, having been at Glouceſter for the ſpace of three weeks before, but was perſwaded thereto by the urgent importunity of many of Mr. <hi>Bacons</hi> followers: and he upon whoſe report this aſperſion was grounded, hath ſince acknowledged before witneſſe, that he had done Mr. <hi>Wheeler</hi> wrong. And the Sermon Notes, which were read at the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> acknowledged to be true. As for the Miniſters readineſſe to receive information, we acknowledge that we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalued the buſineſſe too much, and were blame-worthy in neglecting the truth and our ſelves.</p>
               <p>He imputes to <hi>Mr.</hi> Holford, <hi>Mr.</hi> Hodges <hi>and my ſelf the cauſe of his ſummons to the Covernors Chamber on the Lords day.</hi> Whereas it was concluded the day before by the Magiſtrates, when they had once thoughts of ſending him out of Town without more ado. And of this I had not the leaſt intimation, till the meeting was reſolved upon, and the report thereof ſpread about the City, though he ſaith he never heard of it till the time came. And thus doth a veyn of Calumny run through the whole Relation.</p>
               <p>He obſerves that <hi>he was ſent for by a Souldier as a tranſgreſſour.</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113599:6"/>
What a triviall circumſtance, and abſurd collection? Is it not well known, that Souldiers under the Command of a principall Officer are like the Centurions Servants, who ſaid <hi>to one come, and he cometh; to an other go, and he goeth; and to a third do this, and he doth it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This meeting conſiſted of men of quality, common fellows were excluded, except ſome of his own party who were admitted by our conſent; among whom a young preaching Pewterer.</p>
               <p>An other Aſperſion is caſt upon the Miniſters behaviour in time of the Conference, <hi>That they upbraided him with much unbeſeeming and reproachfull language, ruſhing upon him with a torrent of evil words, till that unſeemlineſſe was remedied by the Governors command.</hi> This is a meer ſlander, having nothing of truth, and herein we can appeal to the Governors own teſtimony. A greater Acrimony might eaſily manifeſt it ſelf in a ſerious Conteſt, but without bitter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives; and if ſome did inveigh againſt Hereticks and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks in generall, yet not againſt his perſon. Or if a ſtream of words might flow from divers men, the cauſe of it was his refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of a poſitive Declaration. And if one man at that preſent had nothing to charge him withall, yet there were many Miniſters, and the Controverſie did not depend on the Judgement or mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of one Man. And whereas he ſpeaks of <hi>their laying heads toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> let him know there were ſuch men as ſcorned a Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who walked not in the dark, and can offer themſelves with much boldneſſe to be judged by mans judgement, although he that judgeth us is the Lord.</p>
               <p>But here is the main grievance which he labours to diſplay, <hi>That not finding ſufficient matter of accuſation, we began to examine him upon certain interrogatories: againſt which he proteſted, becauſe it favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo ſtrongly of the illegality of the High Commiſſion Court.</hi> Wherefore to juſtifie our proceedings, we offer theſe things to be weighed by the judicious. Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> was looked upon in the notions either of an Erroneous, or of an obſcure, and ambiguous Preacher, not by reaſon of his profound; but his wavering and doubtfull Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Firſt, he was conſidered as ambiguous, and therefore ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected and dangerous. Which appears in that he did alwayes pretend unto ſomething extraordinary, beyond that which the people had been formerly taught, even concerning the ſubſtance
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113599:7"/>
of fundamentall Doctrine: every mindfull hearer took it for a new way, eſpecially his own favourers, &amp; then the tearms of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Preachers, and Preachers of Chriſt began to be rolled upon every tongue. Beſides, in the explication of any point, he would heap up an infinity of words paſſing to and fro in a conſtrained way, that one might eaſily beleeve, <hi>Male res agitur ubi opus eſt tot remediis.</hi> There was ſtill an expectation of ſome great thing car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried aloft in the Clouds, which a while after fell down in a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſhowre of words. And in ſuch a caſe who can blame the jealouſie of a Miniſter; who muſt watch over the Flock, as one that muſt give an account of their ſouls? Inſinuations of Errour ſlide into the minds of people, when the violent approach of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt opinions begets horror, and ſaves them by fear. Secondly, Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> was lookt upon as an erroneous Preacher: ſome things are hinted already; and the reſt are to be made known, when I come to diſcuſſe the Queſtions. Nevertheleſſe 'tis worthy obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that he was more liberal in private then in publick, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries were unvailed, <hi>imis penetralibus,</hi> becauſe al was not thought fit for a promiſcuous, and unprepar'd Auditory. One inſtance ſhal ſerve, which will be made good by approved teſtimony if need require. In private he diſputed againſt habituall graces, not in the way of Argumentation, but according to his proper Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but in publick ſuch a deſigne muſt be carried on through a maze of intricate and perplexed words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But we are charged in compelling Mr.</hi> Bacon <hi>to a ſelf accuſation, and therein with reviving the aboliſhed tyrannie of the High-Commiſſion.</hi> To this it is anſwered, that we did not require him to betray himſelf, nor to diſcloſe any ſecret concerning him or his, that might make him obnoxious to any mulct or penalty. And had he refuſed to Anſwer, his danger was no more, then the ſcandall of his Doctrine. We did not aſſume a liberty of propoſing Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions <hi>in infinitum,</hi> but ſuch onely as immediately reflected upon his preaching, whereby we were ſcandalized; yea and ſuch things as did ariſe out of his Sermons. And that not ſo much to know his opinion, as to lay down ſome ground-work upon which the debate might reſt. Moreover, did ever any that were exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Authority (ſuppoſe of the Prelates) in the principles of Faith, account that Examination a Tyranny, or a means to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113599:7"/>
enſnare them? Beſides a Miniſter is bound to declare his judgement in the principal matters of Divine knowledge, if meerly deſired by his fellow labourers, whenſoever they are publikely offended, yea though unjuſtly. But there is more yet in this caſe. Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> came as a ſtranger, and though he had the power of a miniſteriall calling, yet he had neither power, nor call to exerciſe his miniſtery againſt the conſent of the Magiſtrates and Miniſters of that place where he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed, And it is provided by Order of Parliament in their Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the Committees of ſome counties, as in <hi>Sommerſet</hi>-ſhire, that every Miniſter placed by them in any Sequeſtred living, ſhal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the examination of three Miniſters in the ſame county. Thus much for the firſt meeting in the Governours Chamber.</p>
               <p>The Queſtions were not propounded as we in our wiſedoms (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his phraſe) thought meet; but as his preaching and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice did require. A Debate upon them was reſerved for Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following, in that place where the Councel of War was wont to be held.</p>
               <p>His tedious mention of many idle circumſtances, I paſſe by, as unbeſeeming a grave Relation. At the place appointed, Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> brought in an Anſwer in writing to the ten Queſtions, as himſelf pleads, according to a former command. But he fails in the truth of the buſineſſe: For an Anſwer in writing was not required, but a Verbal diſpute; though it was thought meet that the Arguments ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on both ſides ſhould be then written, that we might not loſe our ſelves in a Chaos of words. The reading of his Paper, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook of my own accord; for the Governour intended a diſpute, and then chalenged Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> for refuſing. I gave off reading in the midſt, not (as he ſaith) <hi>becauſe unwilling that the company ſhould hear altogether;</hi> but partly, becauſe I was tired with many tedious impertinencies, and longed to make anſwer; partly, becauſe the bare reading of a large Paper, containing ſundry things, could give no ſatisfaction to the people. Nevertheleſſe I examined his ſtating of the Queſtions one by one, by clear argument diſcovering his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and nullities, to which he would give no anſwer, but referr'd all to his Paper, which was then Refuted. If there were confuſion of language, that was cauſed by his obſtinate ſilence. For who could endure ſo groſſe a tergiverſation, accompanied with a ſelf-juſtification to the higheſt?</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113599:8"/>
               <p n="2">2. Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> here and elſewhere complains <hi>of reproachful lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage from the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niſters.</hi> But I muſt anſwer him, <hi>In generalibus verſatur doloſus.</hi> Let him give an inſtance of ſuch Reviling. I can juſtifie my ſelf, neither do I remember any railing accuſation that then fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l from the mouth of a Miniſter. But if any of them did vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently charge him with the ſhame of a ſelf-baffle, ſhall that be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reproach? Thoſe Miniſters are more ingenuous and of better ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, then this R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>later deſires to render them. I could not obſerve, nor remember every paſſage that fell from thoſe in Authority, or from the ſtanders by. Neither do I juſtifie their threats, if there were any. But his perſon was no more endangered then ours, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be may pretend or intimate. As for that Gentleman whom he reports to be of no mean command, though his <hi>Military</hi>-Office were not in the Gariſon, I can ſay little to his words what they were. He hath been an ancient profeſſor of Religion, and of approved integrity. But if it be ſaid that the people called him <hi>Bonner,</hi> it muſt be the greater part, or the better part, or at leaſt a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part. But the ſpeech of one Woman, he is pleaſed to attribute to the people. So greedily doth our oppoſite catch at every cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, though ſtrangely miſrepreſented. He addes, that <hi>beſides divers Miniſters, one a Cavalier openly jeered him.</hi> This is a malicious ſlander: let him name the perſons. That Miniſter which was taken in arms againſt the Parliament, had voluntarily taken the Covenant, and therupon obtained his liberty: but he had no hand in the manage of this buſineſſe, being a ſpectator onely: and for his open jeering, if it be true, as I queſtion, others could not prevent that incivility.</p>
               <p>In the cloſe of this unweldy Conflict, a writing was drawn up, <hi>That</hi> Mr. <hi>Bacon had divulged certain erroneous Opinions, in which at a Conference he had given no ſatisfaction:</hi> The Auditors were to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe if they pleaſed. But he declares, the reaſon of this Subſcription was, <hi>to ſend him up to the Parliament or Aſſembly the next day.</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that I knew not of any ſuch thought, and am aſſured, that the Governour did not intend it; but I conceive that he grounds his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion upon ſome wandring ſpeeches ſcattered among the people: But this is the truth of the buſineſſe; We have had great experience of the vain boaſtings of Sectaries, who to wound the Reputation of thoſe that encounter them, proclaime a Victory and ſing the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, what ever the ſucceſſe be. This was then feared from that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113599:8"/>
Party; to prevent which miſchief, a Subſcription was then thought upon, and firſt hinted by a moderate man, no Miniſter, nor at that time a Magiſtrate. And to this none were compelled: onely, when we had a meeting, for ſatisfaction, we deſired to know the opinion of the Auditors. And of thoſe Six perſons that refuſed to Subſcribe, ſome pretended that they did not heare, others that they were not preſent at the whole Conference, one or two would give no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: but none of them did avow to have received any ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>That the manner of our proceedings <hi>were generally complained of</hi> (as is related) <hi>and accounted neither Christian nor juſtifiable by the Law of civill Society,</hi> is a groſſe calumny; and herein I appeale to the Inhabitants of that place. What one man, namely, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Shepard,</hi> might in private acknowledge is nothing to our purpoſe. Thus much for the ſecond meeting.</p>
               <p>The Mayor with others are ſaid to ſpend much time in perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to depart the City: affirming, <hi>if he were the moſt Orthodox Preacher in England, he were not fit for Gloceſter.</hi> Thus they ſpeak upon bare ſuppoſition. And the conſequence drawn from hence is moſt abſurd, namely, <hi>that an Orthodox Preacher ſhould be a burden too heavy for Gloceſter to bear.</hi> If M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bacon</hi> ſuppoſed to be an Orthodox Preacher, be not fit for ſuch a place, doth it therefore follow that no Orthodox Preacher is fit? Is Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> and Orthodox Preacher con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible? Experience witneſſeth, that not only Orthodox, but ſome good men may not be fit for ſome Congregations. Beſides this thing doth aſſure us of his importunate contradiction, who would ſtay in a place where he had no intereſt, when the Magiſtrate deſired his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and perſwaded his departure upon this ground, that he was not a man fit for Gloceſter. But he ſaith, <hi>He feared the deſertion of his owne or rather Chriſts Cauſe. Anſw.</hi> Is the Cauſe of Chriſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by a troubleſome preſence in deſpite of the Magiſtrate? Tis enough, that a man makes anſwer in a free confeſſion and ſubmits to the cenſure of Authority.</p>
               <p>The Relation proceeds to the publicke Diſputation; for which purpoſe there was an Order from the Governour directed to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Miniſters to be read in the Pulpit, <hi>That if any doubted of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provedneſſe of the proceedings in the two former meetings, ſatisfaction ſhould be given in a more publicke way.</hi> This Order I received as I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113599:9"/>
was going into the Pulpit, without the leaſt intimation or thought thereof before, though the Diſpute would reſt upon me. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was moved hereunto not to terrifie Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> as he doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in the expreſſions of his great thoughts of heart; But upon the advertizement of falſe Reports raiſed by his followers. Here as in many other places a heape of circumſtances are brought in being more fit for an idle Romance, then a ſerious diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Governour, and Mr.</hi> Bromwitch <hi>of the Committee are ſaid to engage themſelves to protect him from ſlander and wrong, which the one heard, and the other ſaw he formerly ſuſtained.</hi> He makes it the ſenſe of the Governour that he had ſuſtained wrong, which is knowne in Gloceſter to be a manifeſt untruth, and cannot be rationally concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by any that knew that buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſpeaks of a Marſhall ſtanding at his elbow with a Halbert though he perceived it not, of purpoſe, if it might be to daunt him.</hi> I obſerved no ſuch thing, ſtanding oppoſite and likely to behold his attendance: the Governour proteſts againſt it; and to ſtand with a Halbert, is not a Marſhal's poſture. Beſides, it was ſo much inviſible, that Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> obſerved it not, which could not well have been if any had ſtood there in <hi>terrorem.</hi> And is it not a childiſh conceit, that a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſhould be terrified by a Marſhal with a Halbert; and an explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded folly to bleſſe God for his aſſiſtance that he was not daunted thereby?</p>
               <p>The way of the Diſpute in general, was on this manner. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Queſtions; Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> affirmed or denied, and read the ſtating of them: I read my written Reply, thence drawing conciſe Arguments, to which he made large Declarations. It ſeems we muſt give him leave to proclaim and glory <hi>that his Adverſaries fell before him, to the great contentment and ſatisfaction of the believing and more ſober-minded people.</hi> But it had been better that his neighbours mouth had praiſed him. Doth he not arrogate very much, that all the believing people ſhould rejoyce at his clearing? Let theſe abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities confute themſelves. He ſpeaks of <hi>Diſcontent that appeared in the faces of his adverſaries.</hi> Who made him a judge of our thoughts?</p>
               <p>But it is ſaid, <hi>Master</hi> Corbet <hi>confeſſed before all the people, that it had been better never to have begun ſuch a task; for the people will run after him much more then before. Anſw.</hi> It's impoſſible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member every word that paſſeth in the heat of diſputation. But
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113599:9"/>
my complaint, whatever it was, was thus grounded. Maſter <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> would diſpute neither in a formal Syllogiſm, nor Enthymeme, nor in any Argumentation truſſed up in a Logical way; but ran tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row many Ambages, and ſeemed to make Speeches with an affected deliberation; and ſtill he craved leave to explain himſelf: which prolixity ſpent the time, loſt the Argument, and confounded the Hearers.</p>
               <p>He tells us <hi>that the evidence of the truth had for the preſent ſtruck a deep ſilence in all his oppoſers.</hi> Here is an abſolute falſhood: For unto his Anſwers I ſtill made Reply, till we were taken off, and cauſed by them that moderated to paſſe to another Queſtion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of Diſputation.</p>
               <p>He relates that <hi>ſome were complained of by witneſſes to have vowed to be the death of him.</hi> Here is an high Charge given in; but to whom the complaint was made, or by what witneſſes, or who thoſe were that had ſo vowed, it is not ſignified. In this he deals deceitfully, lurking in generals, and maliciouſly, in leaving doubtful not onely the perſons, but the conditions of them who ſhould ſo vow: the world might ſuſpect Magiſtrates, Commanders, Miniſters, and men of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. I am not now in <hi>Glouceſter</hi> to enquire into this paſſage: Let it therefore be thought upon, that I ſtand upon great diſadvantage in this Reply, whereas a longer time of examination would diſplay my Antagoniſt much more; but that I haſten to cruſh this bird in the ſhell: yet having no more, then what I know to be firm truth at ſuch a diſtance both of time and place, I doubt not but to make a ſufficient diſcovery of his many Untruths, to all indifferent judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Wherefore I know that men of any value would highly ſcorn ſuch an Imputation; nor were any incenſed or encouraged by us ſo much as unto violent ſpeeches. And if this were true, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Maſter <hi>Bacon,</hi> who hath ſtuffed his book with ſo many idle paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſages, would not omit to give ſome character of the perſons guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo great a crime.</p>
               <p>Thus ended the firſt days Diſpute: The morrow after, we came together to diſcuſſe the reſidue of the Queſtions. But our Relator gives out that <hi>the remaining part of my Reply,</hi> i. e. <hi>to the five laſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, contained little elſe then invectives againſt his perſon.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I charge him with a notorious ſlander. And if my charge be falſe, 'tis in his power to ſhame me: For my Reply was delivered
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113599:10"/>
in to him, and had now been printed, had my papers been by me.</p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> had no more diſcountenance the ſecond day then the firſt; onely he was required to contract his ſpeech according to the law of Argumentation; and even then, he ſpake many words for my one.</p>
               <p>But he ſaith that <hi>the Committee being Judge, in their name (as he ſuppoſeth) Maſter</hi> Bromwitch <hi>drew up the reſult of each days diſpute, and gave the whole Aſſ mbly notice that nothing was proved againſt him, but what was according to Orthodox opinion.</hi> To this I make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That the Governour, the Maior, and Aldermen, were Judges as well as the Committee, and that Maſter <hi>Bromwitch,</hi> as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, did not ſpeak in the name of the Committee, but in his own name, being a quick and a nimble Diſputant. Beſides, this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman did not take off the charge of Errour: but when M ſter <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> running to and fro in doubtful terms, came neer to our Tenents, he read it to the people, rather to his conviction then clearing; by which all men might take notice of his Vacillation or halting. Whether the Committee did ſo clear him, I refer the Reader to their ſecond Order for his removal, which is inſerted in his Relation in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We the Gentlemen of the Committee gave out our Order upon a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Debate, not of our ſelves, as according to our Inſtructions we might have done, but with the ingredients and conſult of many godly and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Miniſters by both parties, and emergent Reaſons our Votes were concluded, and</hi> (in a more civil manner then Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> deſerved) <hi>were ſent unto him: yet, although he hath rather arraigned, then intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Committee to alter their Judgements, we are reſolved not to alter our commands, as rather engaged to gratifie ſo many Orthodox Divines then his fancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He remarks the word <hi>gratifie.</hi> What greater reproach could he faſten upon the Committee, then thus to inſinuate that they did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure him to gratifie us?</p>
               <p>But it is ſaid <hi>that Maſter</hi> Corbet <hi>with all vehemency exclaimed that Maſter</hi> Bacon <hi>had another meaning, though his words were juſtifiable.</hi> It is anſwered, that I did not juſtifie the greateſt part of his expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, though ſome of them might admit a fair conſtruction. But I complained of the ambiguity of his expreſſions, which were not fit for Diſpute, though they may ſuit very well with Exhortation.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113599:10"/>
And when a man ſhall abſolutely diſclain ſuch terms as are neceſſary to Diſputation, 'tis no fair dealing, nor ſigne of a good cauſe or ſound Doctrine. To make inſtance; at that very time he would by no means meddle with the terms of the habits of grace, or inherent holineſſe, becauſe they were not Scripture-terms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Miniſters got themſelves into a committee that afternoon,</hi> is utterly falſe. For they had no meeting among themſelves. Wherefore that <hi>Maſter</hi> Hart <hi>and Maſter</hi> Cloſe <hi>were exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ded by conſent,</hi> is as falſe. As alſo, <hi>that we ſhould reſolve among our ſelves</hi> (as the Relation imports) <hi>that he muſt depart, or we would leave the city,</hi> is a groſſe untruth. We had no ſuch Debate, no ſuch circumſtances, no ſuch meeting. But the Miniſters were required to attend the Committee of Parliament. And if Maſter <hi>Hart</hi> and Maſter <hi>Cloſe</hi> were not there, their own unwillingneſſe was the cauſe of their non-appearance.</p>
               <p>The Committee are able to juſtifie their own Orders, and their manner of proceeding. Threatnings, if they were, or whatever they were, were provoked by his obſtinate diſobedience.</p>
               <p>What a train of egregious ſtories brings up the rere of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>of things done upon a Saturday at two a clock in the afternoon, by the Governours Captain Lieutenant with a party of Troopers, and their diſcourſe with him; with his ſeverall Horſes; the Captain Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant's leaving him at three miles diſtance from the city; his guidance by the Head-corporal; and that Captain</hi> Maſſie <hi>did not go in his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to</hi> Sudely, <hi>but came after late in the night,</hi> &amp;c. Such ſtrains will help to ſwell the Volume of a jeſting Romance, or Book of Knight-Errantry.</p>
               <p>But I obſerve that Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> doth not ſo fairly alight from off that horſe that was taken up to convey him to ſome other of the Parliaments Quarters; nor doth he ſufficiently clear himſelf from that fraud he ſaith was laid to his charge. This is the truth of the ſtory: Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> diſliking the firſt horſe, was furniſhed with another more able. Himſelf reports that his guides having brought him to <hi>Warwick,</hi> told him that they had no order con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the horſe, but that it was at his own diſpoſal. This was either their neglect or diſhoneſty. And could he think that thoſe Souldiers had power to give another mans horſe taken up for that particular ſervice? or did he conceive that the Governour would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113599:11"/>
either defraud the owner, or pay the price that he might be quit his company? But this horſe was chalenged at <hi>London</hi> on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of Colonel <hi>Okey,</hi> at that time in Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> Army, at the inſtance of Colonel <hi>Okey</hi>'s friend, by Maſter <hi>Wheeler,</hi> who had an intereſt in that Army: and imported as much to Maſter <hi>Bacon.</hi> But he refuſed to reſtore it: and being demanded to declare his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt therein, he replied that the horſe was at his diſpoſal, and that he had endeavoured to put him off or exchange him at <hi>Northampton.</hi> Hereupon he was chalenged for a fellonious detainer, and ſtill urged to give him back, even by the owners wife, till for meer ſhame, and the importunity of his own friends, to avoid further ſcandal, he was compelled to deliver him. This paſſage at <hi>London,</hi> is avowed by Maſter <hi>Wheeler</hi> in all the circumſtances.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>he calls God, and the conſciences of thoſe that were preſent, to witneſſe the truth of his Relation.</hi> I alſo can appeal to heaven for the truth of my Anſwer; wherein my adverſary is convicted of ſo many falſhoods and impertinencies; and am alſo aſſured of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the Magiſtrates and the Miniſters of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> which was the Scene of this Action.</p>
               <p>Concerning theſe ten Queſtions, let it be conſidered, firſt, that they were propounded without any premeditation; and many of them were not expreſſed in ſuch ſearching terms, as might prevent all evaſions. Secondly, that we condeſcended to <hi>Mr. Bacon</hi> in the wording of them, becauſe he would not be gained to declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, except he apprehended ſome advantage. Thirdly, that <hi>Maſter Bacon</hi> hath publiſhed his ſtating of them, and that with a plentiful Commentary upon ſome; but omitted my Anſwer not onely given in private, but debated upon in publike. The copie thereof I have not by me; and the neceſſity of a quick diſpatch permits no delay. But the ſubſtance thereof is faithfully delivered: if not, my oppoſite having the Paper put into his hands, may diſcover it if he pleaſe. Fourthly, the Affirmative and Negative affixed, is <hi>Maſter Bacons</hi> Judgement. Let ours be collected in the diſcuſſe of each Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113599:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. 1.</hi> Whether the Morall Law be abrogated? <hi>Neg.</hi> according to Master <hi>B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the tearmes we agree, but he ſtates the Queſtion by ſeverall Aphoriſmes, that ſcarſe approach the true meaning thereof; which is, whether we are bound to the Morall as a rule of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>He ſaith firſt, <hi>The Morall Law was revealed from heaven of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on Mount Sinai, and in that conſideration is to be had in high honour and account.</hi> This doth not reſolve the queſtion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Tis a part of the holy Scriptures, and therefore not to be ſleighted.</hi> So is the Cerimoniall Law.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Tis the image of God, ſo that by the Law we may ſee the holineſſe and righteouſneſſe of God.</hi> Neither is the doubt here reſolved, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are bound to obſerve the Morall Law, as a rule of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Chriſt was ſhadowed out in the Law.</hi> The Ceremoniall Law was a ſhadow of Chriſt, not the Morall. Secondly, grant this, and the Morall Law hath herein no more priviledg then <hi>the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimoniall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>All the world ſhall be judged by it.</hi> This doth not come to the ſtate of the queſtion; for the Reprobate ſhall be judged accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rigor of that law; and the Elect by the ſame law as fulfilled in Chriſt. But this ſatisfies not whether it remaines a binding rule of obedience.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Thoſe, that beleeve in Jeſus, walke more freely in the things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the Law, then they are without Chriſt.</hi> Still from the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſe. Secondly, thoſe that without Chriſt doe nothing truely and ſincerely, which is contained in the Law.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>The Law is exceeding uſefull to take men off from the damnable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their owne righteouſneſſe.</hi> This doth neither declare that a Chriſtian ought to humble his ſoule by reflecting up the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Law of an holy and jealous God, nor that he is bound to the Law as a Rule.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>The Law in the Hand of a Mediator is a rule of life; for what the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113599:12"/>
Law doth command in the letter, that the law of the ſpirit of life doth worke within, which is therefore called the Law of Faith, or the Law of Chriſt, or the Law written in the heart.</hi> Here he ſeems to ſpeak ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but all darke and confuſed. The Law in it ſelfe, and not as conſidered in the hand of a Mediator, is the rule of life: But the Law given in the hand of a Mediator doth ſhew that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act righteouſneſſe thereof is not required unto juſtification. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he brings a reaſon which hath no connexion in theſe words, <hi>For what the Law doth command in the letter without, the law of the ſpirit doth worke within;</hi> except he doth meane, becauſe the Goſpell inableth, the Law bindeth. Is this to ſtate a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted queſtion. Might not an Antinomian grant theſe poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons if he would ſtudy to conceale himſelfe?</p>
               <p>Beſides, at the Diſpute he did reject this Concluſion, viz. <hi>That the Law doth bind a Chriſtian to obedience; for,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell doth inable him.</hi> Which the underſtanding hearers remember (I doubt not) that I refuted, by replying, that tis the nature of a Law to binde; and where the Law bindes not, there is no ſin. Have we not reaſon to ſuſpect unſoundneſſe in this Point? And as there is a diſtinction made between ſeperation and ſemi-ſeperation, ſo tis neceſſary to diſtinguiſh between groſſe and cloſe Antinomianiſme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. 2.</hi> Whether good Workes be a meanes to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Salvation. <hi>Neg.</hi> according to Maſter <hi>B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HErein we differ. But this queſtion was at firſt propoſed in other tearmes. <hi>Whether good Works may be called a Way to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> which Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> had formerly denyed to my ſelfe and another Miniſter, and at the firſt Conference more publikly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed the diſtinction of <hi>Via ad Regnum,</hi> and <hi>Cauſa Regnandi,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that Jeſus Chriſt is the onely way: Whereas we meane by a way, ſuch a courſe as God hath appointed them to take, whom he will bring to ſalvation, without which ſalvation doth not enſue. As the narrow way in the Goſpell, and the undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the way, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. And by good workes we declared to underſtand not onely the fruits, but the principles of holineſſe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113599:12"/>
namely, inherent grace. But to indulge our adverſary in an expreſſion, the Queſtion was thus propounded, Whether good Workes be a meanes to obtaine Salvation: By which we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not the onely, or the chiefeſt meanes; for I then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in my Paper, that Chriſt alone by his ſuper-abounding merit hath purchaſed ſalvation for us; and now further adde, that according to his pleaſure he diſpenſeth his grace, and by his power preſerveth his people to eternall life. But holineſſe is ſo neceſſary, that if ſuppoſing an impoſſibility, a man might be juſtified and not ſanctified, he could never appeare before the face of God in glory.</p>
               <p>But this expreſſion is rejected <hi>as unſavoury;</hi> whereas a meanes doth imply no more, then ſomething aptly diſpoſed and deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a certain end.</p>
               <p>Thus Gods Ordinances are a means to obtain ſalvation. But holineſſe is abſolutely neceſſary; follow peace with all men, and holineſſe without which no man ſhal ſee the Lord. But the word obtaine is moſt remarked, which is the Scripture phraſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. <hi>So run that ye may obtaine.</hi> Conſider other places, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Worke out your ſalvation with feare and trembling. Phil.</hi> 3.14. it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the reward of victory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>our light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction which is but for a moment, worketh out for us a far more exceeding weight of glory.</hi> That holineſſe is a way to ſalvation is cleerly proved out of the Text which Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> urgeth, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Wee are created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good workes, which God hath ordained that we ſhould walke therein:</hi> for if we walke in them they are a way; if a way, there muſt <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> the end of our walking, which is ſalvation.</p>
               <p>But ſaith he, to affirme <hi>that good workes are a meanes to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſalvation, is to deny Chriſt the onely meanes.</hi> I anſwer, Chriſt is the onely meanes meritorious, and the onely meanes princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally efficient; but this doth not exclude other means ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate unto Chriſt, as the Word and Sacraments, and ſuch things as flow from Chriſt by inevitable conſequence, as good workes being ranked in their own place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113599:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. 3.</hi> Whether God be diſpleaſed with his people that are in Chriſt for their ſinnes, we meane ſuch a people as are in the Covenant of Grace: <hi>Neg.</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Master <hi>B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre we differ in opinion; but this queſtion was at firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in other tearms, <hi>viz. Whether God be diſpleaſed with the ſinnes of his people?</hi> which Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> affirmed: Whereupon we urged his owne Doctrine publickly taught in theſe words: <hi>You know that when we pleaſe men, they will be pleaſed with us, when we offend them, they will bee offended with us; they are up and downe, but farre be it from us to entertaine ſuch thoughts of God; whom he loveth he loveth to the end, he is not as man to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed; the Lord help us, that we rather conſider, that we are not ſinners ſo much becauſe of the acts of ſinne, but rather becauſe of the ſinfulneſſe of ſinne: It is true, to the naturall man, to our underſtandings, God is pleaſed with us this houre and not that houre; but you muſt come up higher to the knowledge of God, that he is the ſame to day and for ever.</hi> Here he plainly denies the pleaſure or diſpleaſure of God for this or or that act; and hereupon he brought forth this ſubtilty; That God is diſpleaſed with the ſinnes of his people, but not with his people for ſinne; of which people he exacted ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation, as that they are in Chriſt, as if we conceived Gods people out of Chriſt; but this is not enough, he exacts more, <hi>viz.</hi> we meane ſuch a people as are in the Covenant of grace, as if it were poſſible to conceive that Gods people which are in Chriſt are out of the Covenant of grace: He ſtates the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on this wiſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>When we affirme that God is diſpleaſed or angry, we ſpeak after the manner of men, for God is not ſubject to paſſion: Anſw.</hi> to ſay that God is angry is ſpoken after the manner of men; yet diſpeaſure is no paſſion, but agrees with God in the higheſt perfection of his nature; for God is equally perfect in the diſlike of ſinne, as in the love of good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>When we are chastened of the Lord, 'tis a ſigne of his love, not of his diſpleaſure: Anſw.</hi> Gods love is not oppoſed to his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113599:13"/>
but to hatred: Yea, the more love the more diſpleaſure when we ſinne againſt love; This in Parents is the fruit of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall affection.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Tis moſt peremptorily to be affirmed, that God hates ſin in whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever:</hi> This is true; but we ſpeak of diſpleaſure not of hatred.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>So farre as the children of God live off from Chriſt, and walk un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the Goſpell, ſo farre they lye under the ſenſe of wrath; inſomuch as the Apoſtle ſaith, he ſcourgeth every ſonne whom he loves; it's impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that a man ſhould have peace in the wayes of ſinne: Anſw.</hi> Here he contradicts and refutes himſelfe, and runs out beyond our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: The children of God walking unworthy of the Goſpell, doe not alwayes in ſuch a caſe lye under the ſenſe of wrath, which is the apprehenſion of the guilt of ſinne binding them to eternall vengeance; &amp; which is as farre diſtant from the bare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of diſpleaſure, as the ſpirit of Bondage from the ſpirit of Adoption: Where the Apoſtle ſaith, he ſcourgeth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſonne whom he receiveth, he doth not meane the ſenſe of wrath: But he addes, <hi>'tis impoſſible that a man ſhould have peace in the wayes of ſinne;</hi> whence I inferre, where there is no peace, and ſo ought to be no ſenſe of peace, there Gods diſpleaſure muſt needs be apprehended (for when God is not diſpleaſed, there is peace in the ſoule) and if we muſt apprehend the Lords diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, he is really diſpleaſed, except we are bound to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend a falſhood: Many times the Saints apprehend diſpleaſure when God is pleaſed, but they are never bound ſo to doe, but when God is actually diſpleaſed; therefore it doth neceſſarily follow, that if there were no peace in the wayes of ſinne, God muſt needs be diſpleaſed with his people for ſinne.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The fift paragraph is anſwered in the former.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The ſixt is exceeding tedious and confuſed; the ſubſtance thereof I collect and examine: <hi>That a naturall man looking upon God in the Law, apprehends he pleaſeth God ſo farre as he keeps the Law, and ſo farre as he comes ſhort of obedience to the Law, ſo farre he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends he deſpleaſeth God: But a ſpirituall man ſeeing himſelfe accepted of God in Chriſt, ought not to conceive that God is up and downe with him in his love, for whom he loves he loves to the end. Anſw.</hi> Gods love is oppoſed to hatred, not to diſpleaſure; the love of our perſons
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113599:14"/>
and a temporary diſpleaſure conceived againſt our perſons are well conſiſtent, as in the caſe of paternall affection: Secondly, God is ſaid to be angry with <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I demand whether <hi>Moſes,</hi> being in the Covenant of grace, was bound to beleeve Gods diſpleaſure upon Gods owne mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation, or whether he did diſhonour God by beleeving, that he was diſpleaſed with him (as Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> imports a beleever doth in ſuch a caſe?) That ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. is the everlaſting love of God, abounding to the acceptance our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and performances, yea the love of complacency, which doth not exclude the particular acts of diſpleaſure, and the way of attonement and redintegration after our fals.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The ſeventh proves nothing, but that being reconciled, we are ſaved from wrath, <hi>viz.</hi> divine revenge, which we grant.</p>
               <p>But in the laſt place, he doth extreamly ſubtillize his Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; he is contented that <hi>God ſhould be diſpleaſed with ſinne, but not with the ſinner:</hi> It is true, that in ſome caſes God doth hate ſin, but not the ſinner; as a father hates the diſobedience of his ſon, but hates not his ſonne in diſobedience; for hatred is the extreameſt alienation; but diſpleaſure is an act of diſlike not of alienation: Now a man may diſlike his friend, but never hate him in the notion of a friend; and he muſt needs diſlike him when he offends againſt the bond of friendſhip, though that bond be not broken; and a father that is diſpleaſed with his childs rebellion, muſt needs be diſpleaſed with his child that rebels.</p>
               <p>To conclude, if God be in no caſe diſpleaſed with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they need not confeſſe that by ſinne they have provoked him to diſpleaſure: Under moſt grievous fals their condition is as good towards God as ever; they are bound even then to apprehend the light of his countenance, and the brightneſſe of his glory ſhining upon them, and by conſequence <hi>David</hi> was as much accepted with God, and might have conceived as much ſpirituall joy in the bed of adultery with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> as after that great humbling of his ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113599:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. 4.</hi> Whether thoſe in the Covenant of grace are to try their Juſtification by their Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Aff.</hi> according to Maſter <hi>B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre we agree in the tearmes, but whether in the thing it ſelf it's very doubtfull. When we propounded this queſtion we did conceive that Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> would put no other meaning upon the tearme Sanctification the inherent holineſſe: But we juſtly ſuſpect ſome other ſenſe; firſt, becauſe he doth here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret holineſſe to be <hi>that ſeed of God which John ſaith abideth in every one that is borne of God,</hi> 2 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. and at the diſputation, by this ſeed, he did underſtand the ſpirit; againſt which inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation I made reply, that the ſeed of God muſt be the work of the Spirit, and not the ſpirit it ſelfe: Secondly, in that he ſaith, <hi>That which is done</hi> in foro Coeli, <hi>in the Court of Heaven, is done alſo</hi> in foro conſcientiae, <hi>in the Court of Conſcience by the Spirit of Chriſt, and where the ſpirit of Chriſt is, there are the fruits of the Spirit, goodneſſe, righteouſneſſe, truth.</hi> This is true in it ſelfe; but it doth not cleere unto our underſtanding, but that he meanes by San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, the inhabitation of the Spirit, by whoſe ſole teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony our juſtification muſt be evidenced, and that goodneſſe, truth and righteouſneſſe are the immediate workings of a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall ſpirit by which we are over-acted, and not of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall graces: I doe not directly charge him with this meaning in theſe words of his, but they doe not evince the contary; and the paſſages forementioned hold forth grounds of jealouſie: Beſides, I know that thoſe of his party doe much undervalue, if not wholly deny the uſe of Markes and Signes in this Triall.</p>
               <p n="2">2 In the ſecond Paragraph I aſſent unto him in this, <hi>That when I doe ſome good actions, I muſt not therefore beleeve my Juſtification:</hi> but I diſſent from him in the other part, wherein he ſaith, <hi>when I faile in ſome works to ſuſpect my justification, tends to overthrow the glorious work of Justification:</hi> Had he ſaid that a Chriſtian is not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113599:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113599:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113599:16"/>
thence abſoluetly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, that he is not juſtified, he had ſaid right; but to ſay that he muſt not ſuſpect his juſtification when he failes in ſome works (as to inſtance <hi>David</hi> in adultery, <hi>Peter</hi> in denying Chriſt, which were failings in ſome works) is no ſound nor ſafe Doctrine. That height and glory of faith, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in hope againſt hope, is not exerciſed in the ſlighting of our ſinnes, but in a great deſertion, and the want of a ſpirituall fight to behold the brightneſſe of the Lord ſhining upon us. Or when Faith revives a man from under the ſad apprehenſion of his fall or backſliding, it is done, when he hath made ſearch after his former evidences, and diſcernes at leſt the root of grace alive in the ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q. 5.</hi> Whether Faith be a condition of the new Covenant, <hi>Neg.</hi> according to Master <hi>B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. HEre we differ in opinion. Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> thus differenceth the Covenant of works and the Covenant of grace, <hi>That the one promiſeth life upon condition, the other gives it upon free pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Anſw.</hi> The difference of the Covenants was wont to be made by their conditions. In the firſt, life is promiſed upon condition of workes; in the ſecond, upon condition of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. The ſame place which works had in the firſt Covenant, faith hath obtained in the new. There is a law of works and a law of faith: Faith is the Goſpell duty, and unbeleefe is the maine Goſpell ſinne. But let us examine the difference made by him. <hi>The Covenant of workes promiſeth life upon condition, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gives it of free promiſe. Anſw.</hi> A free promiſe doth not deny all conditioning; as, <hi>To as many as received him, to them he gave power to become the ſonnes of God, even to them that beleeve on his name;</hi> neither doth the free promiſe exclude the condition of Faith; for the Law of Faith is free of the higheſt grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude boaſting and bondage.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>We are not required to the ratification of the Covenant to bring faith to God, but the new Covenant is to give us faith to bring us to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Anſw.</hi> Neither to the ratification of the firſt Covenant were we
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113599:16"/>
required to bring works to God, nor did any works before the Covenant merit or make way for the promiſe of life upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of works. But God in the very making of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant gave man abilitie to perform the tenure thereof. On the ſame manner ſuppoſing Faith to be the Condition of the new Covenant, it doth not infer, that we muſt bring faith to God, but 'tis moſt neceſſarie that God work faith in us to the ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant. Faith is not pre-required in the way of merit, or previous diſpoſition, but at the very inſtant, when God ſtrikes Covenant with the ſoul, faith, though freely given, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to the exiſtence of that Covenant. And whereas he ſaith, <hi>The Covenant doth not depend upon our beleeving, but upon Gods promiſe and faithfulneſſe.</hi> I anſwer: The Covenent doth depend upon Gods promiſe as the ground, and upon our beleeving as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. To prove that the Covenant doth not depend upon our beleeving as a Condition, he urgeth 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. <hi>If we beleeve not, yet he abideth faithfull, and cannot deny himſelf.</hi> If he will draw thence any thing to his purpoſe, he muſt thus expound it, if we beleeve not, yet he will give life unto us becauſe he abideth faithfull, and cannot deny himſelf. Whereas the ſenſe is manifeſt, if we beleeve not, yet he abideth faithfull, and will make good his promiſes to them who by faith receive them.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>In the new Covenant God tyes himſelf, and not the Creature. Anſ.</hi> The eſſentiall form of a Covenant requires the binding of both parties. But how doth he prove this paradox? <hi>Becauſe we are in Gods keeping, and not in our own.</hi> Is not this ſound reaſoning? We are in Gods keeping; therefore God tyes us not. Or becauſe God doth uphold us above the power of falling away, therefore we are not bound to perſevere in beleeving. And if God tyes not the Creature, he hath let looſe the rains to all licentiouſneſſe. In the laſt clauſe he ſaith, <hi>That faith is urged in the Miniſtery of the Goſpel, and given to them that ſhall be ſaved, becauſe no man is juſtified in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God till he doth beleeve. Anſ.</hi> Here we have an Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian principle, that Faith doth not receive and apply our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, but ſerves onely to read our pardon. Secondly, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds Juſtification before God, and that before Conſcience, which are diſtinct notions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="question">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113599:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu. 6.</hi> Whether godly ſorrow for ſin be required of ſuch a one as is the Covenant of grace. Aff: according to Mr. <hi>Bacon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We agree in the tearms of the Queſtion: but firſt I ſhall obſerve that Mr. <hi>Bacons</hi> preaching did rather tend to undermine godly ſorrow. He had theſe paſſages. <hi>Phariſaicall Repentance doth conſiſt in Contrition, Confeſſion, Humiliation, and Satisfaction. Firſt in Contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> (i.) <hi>brokenneſſe of heart, thus the great Phariſees of the world ſpeak of it. That there muſt be in thoſe, that do repent before they be accepted of Chriſt, Contrition enough</hi> (i.) <hi>brokenneſſe of heart, before they come to Chriſt. Now I would fain know when we ſhould come to brokenneſſe of heart enough, that we may be judged fit to come to Chriſt. I think none of them are able to give ſatisfaction.</hi> And a little after. <hi>You muſt not think to get a broken heart before you have got Chriſt, but having Chriſt he will give you a Broken heart.</hi> Here he makes Contrition a part of Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall Repentance, and accounts them the great Phariſees of the time who require Contrition enough before men be accepted of Chriſt. But thoſe Preachers who in Mr. <hi>Bacons</hi> eſteem are Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, do teach that true Contrition is wrought in reſpect of time neither before nor after the receiving of Chriſt: but at the ſame inſtant, without which there is no coming to Chriſt; though he ſaith it is wrought after. When Chriſt proclaims, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are heavy laden,</hi> can any then come to Chriſt till he hath a Broken heart? And Contrition enough is required not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of quantitie and meaſure, but for quality and kind, which is wont to be ſet forth by quantitative tearms, becauſe 'tis a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, deeper, and more piercing ſorrow then all worldly mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and the greateſt howlings of Hypocrites.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas he now ſaith, that <hi>godly ſorrow is required in caſe of ſin:</hi> he hath expreſly declared the contrary in the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sermon in theſe words. <hi>Humiliation, for we ſpeak of Phariſaicall Repentance, for theſe things are ſpoken of thoſe that repent to Salvation but in an other way, is a certain caſting down of a man or woman becauſe of ſin, or the evill that doth accompany it. This is found in Hypocrites and unbeleevers.</hi> Gen. 4. Matth. 6.16. Iſa. 58. <hi>By this dejectment they think to come into the favour of God; but by it may come into the disfavour of God. I ſhall deſcribe that Humiliation, that is approved by God, and found in the Saints. It is a dejectment of a mans ſelf upon the ſight, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113599:17"/>
knowledge of the glory, greatneſſe, power, and goodneſſe of God in Chriſt Jeſus. So that as the knowledge of God in Chriſt doth increaſe in the ſoul, the ſoul is abaſed, as</hi> Iſa. 6. four firſt verſes. Thus he declares Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall humiliation to be a caſting down of a man becauſe of ſin: the Saints humiliation to ariſe from the ſight of the glory of God; where as now he ſaith, godly ſorrow is required in caſe of ſin. How can he reconcile this contradiction? We hold that the ſoul is graciouſly humbled in the ſight of ſin, together with the reflection of the glory of God. Which the Text in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. would have cleared unto him, had he took in the latter part, <hi>viz. I am undone, I am a man of unclean lips, and dwell amongst a people of unclean lips.</hi> Now let it be well conſidered whether this be to handle Gods Word ſincerely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu. 7.</hi> Whether Confeſſion of ſin <hi>(i.)</hi> of ur originall corruption, and ſinfull actions reckoning them before the Lord be required in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Aff. according to M. <hi>B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre we agree in the tearms at leaſt, but in the ſtating of the Queſtion I ſhall briefly obſerve ſome impertinencies, and ſo paſſe on. <hi>Firſt, that Hypocrites are wont to confeſſe their ſinfull actions, but not their ſinfulneſſe: the Saints confeſſe not onely their ſinfull Actions, but their ſinfulneſſe.</hi> Now by ſinfulneſſe he doth underſtand their unclean natures. But know we not that Hypocrites as well as the Saints confeſſe their ſinfull natures, as their ſinfull actions? and in this they differ, that the one confeſſe both theſe in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, the other confeſſe both in ſinceritie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He addeth, <hi>The Confeſſion of the Saints is grounded upon the knowledge of Gods love in Chriſt: but the confeſſion of the Hypocrites upon ſome other information. Anſ.</hi> Is not the Confeſſion of the Saints grounded alſo upon the knowledge of ſin, and of the glory and holineſſe of the Lord, as upon the knowledge of Gods love in Chriſt? Is there any difference between them and Hypocrites in this point, but that they confeſſe upon all the former conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with ſinceritie, and reſolution of amendment of wayes: but Hypocrites upon the ſame conſiderations do not confeſſe from the bottome of their hearts, and with a full purpoſe of Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="question">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113599:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu. 8.</hi> Whether you hold communion with the Church of England <hi>(i.)</hi> in our Parochiall Aſſemblies to be lawfull? Neg. according to Mr. <hi>B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN this we differ. Firſt againſt Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> I reply, that this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not <hi>a matter properly concerning diſcipline,</hi> except matters of diſcipline can deny Communion in the worſhip and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt. Alſo the defects of Reformation is no ground of Separation.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>A ſuppoſition of the peoples not having repented them of their falſe worſhip,</hi> is no ground of ſeparation.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>That he ſhall communicate with any people in any Aſſembly ſo far as reformed according to the Word of God,</hi> is no determinate anſwer.</p>
               <p n="4">4 His Collection from this Queſtion, <hi>That every Pariſh ſhould bear the name of the Church of England is very abſurd.</hi> Becauſe we ſpeak of a Church in Parochiall Aſſemblies as the whole in it's parts, muſt every part bear the name of that whole?</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>That the Church of England doth ceaſe, becauſe diſcipline is for a while ſuſpended,</hi> is a concluſion not worth the refuting.</p>
               <p n="6">6 To underſtand by the Church of England, <hi>all of all Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that have indeed faith towards our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo are of the Church in the eye of God, and are of a ſutable converſation towards men in practice;</hi> is to give a character of a great part of the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church Chriſts myſticall body to a particular conſtituted Church. What more confuſed notions then theſe?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu. 9.</hi> Whether Repentance be neceſſarie to the Remiſſion of ſins. Neg. according to Mr. <hi>B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HErein we diſſent. We underſtand Evangelicall Repentance, and that ſo neceſſarie, as that God will never forgive our ſins untill we repent.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> is very ſubtle in remarking the particle <hi>To.</hi> I cannot underſtand but a thing that is neceſſarie in any determinate caſe muſt be neceſſarie to that thing. But he is afraid that this ſame <hi>To</hi> would bring in Repentance as ſomething actually exiſtent (for ſo I conceive him) before the Remiſſion of ſins. But this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows no more then that we muſt bring faith to God before the Act of Juſtification. But if he will ſay, that we are juſtified by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113599:18"/>
faith, and yet that faith is not neceſſarie to Juſtification, I muſt confeſſe his ſubtilties are beyond my comprehenſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1 For that charge <hi>of bordering nigh unto if not agreeing with that of</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>who affirms, that Repentance is a way to faith and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in the remiſſion of ſins:</hi> If he underſtand it according to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> in the way of a previous diſpoſition, I utterly diſclaim it; Neither can it be collected from the Doctrine of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as neceſſarie to the Remiſſion of ſins. And this anſwers the next Objection, that we make Repentance to go before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins. I give this Inſtance, to have a reaſonable ſoul is neceſſarie to the being of a man, doth it therefore follow that a reaſonable ſoul is before that being? We ſay, that Repentance and Remiſſion are coexiſtent. For at the ſame inſtant, when God doth forgive ſin, he confers the grace of Repentance, that the ſoul might be capable of receiving forgiveneſſe: <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19. Repent and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out. Whereas Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> will have <hi>Remiſſion of ſins to go before Repentance in order of nature.</hi> He cannot reduce it to either of thoſe two wayes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> After one way, that is ſaid to be firſt in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from which the conſequence doth not return to ſome other thing, from whence the conſequence is drawn to that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. To inſtance one is in nature before two. For ſuppoſe two, and one is preſuppoſed; but ſuppoſe one, two doth follow. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that is ſaid to be firſt in nature, <hi>à quo non retro ſequitur conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendi ratio.</hi> Now in this manner Remiſſion of ſins cannot be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Repentance in order of nature, for then upon the ſuppoſal of Remiſſion, Repentance doth not follow. The ſecond way is in reſpect of cauſality. But remiſſion is not the cauſe of repentance. Beſides it ſhould be ſaid, your ſins are forgiven you, that you might repent, and not repent that your ſins might be forgiven. Wherefore Remiſſion of ſins doth require Repentance, as a means abſolutely neceſſarie, and that not pre-exiſtent, but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="question">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:113599:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu. 10.</hi> Whether there be a reall change in the perſon that is ſaved. Aff. according to Mr. B.</head>
               <p>VVE agree in the tearms of the Queſtion, but we have no ſatisfaction therein. Truth is, we were too ſhort in the manner of propounding; we underſtood a reall change not in oppoſition to intentionall onely, but to a relative change alſo, and that none onely a change of condition but of nature. Such a change Mr. <hi>Bacon</hi> did never publickly clear among us. And in the cloſe of this Diſpute he did peremptorily refuſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare whether there were in a beleever the habits of grace, and inherent holineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:113599:19"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
